Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002; 477042
  - CBS News Archives Person to Person with Ed Murrow - "Fidel Castro", 1959 February 6; 467823 (Box 10, Cassette ref230)
  - Contact Lists, 2001; 590720 (Box 72, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 2002; 590721 (Box 72, Folder 3-4)
  - Flyers, circa 2001; 592985 (Box 72, Folder 16)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 1, Fidel addresses Parliament, 1998 September 4; 477182 (Box 70, Cassette ref923, Box 85, Dvd ref923)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:25.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 3, Fidel speaking at Parliament, 1998 September 4; 477183 (Box 70, Cassette ref924, Box 85, Dvd ref924)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: "Cape Town Interview - Parliament", 1998 September 4; 467902 (Box 7, Cassette ref151)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town Speech in Parliament, 1998 September 4; 467903 (Box 7, Cassette ref150, Box 97, Dvd ref150)
    This video features the first portion of a speech by Fidel Castro to the South African parliament in Cape Town, South Africa. Castro begins speaking around minute 5:00. He begins by offering his support and hope for the creation of a new South Africa led by Nelson Mandela, and commends Mandela for his commitment to justice following the end of the apartheid system. Castro calls for an end to divisions on the basis of race, and encourages South Africa and its political leaders to seek to address problems in economic inequality. He discusses the history of colonialism, which led to slavery and exploitation across the globe, expresses his hope that the new South African government will serve as an example of how to break free from the legacy of that system. Audio quality of this video is poor in places.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:58.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 12, various (including Parliament), 1998 September 4; 477184 (Box 69, Cassette ref925, Box 85, Dvd ref925)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:42.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Cape Town 13, Fidel Speech, 1998 September 4; 477185 (Box 69, Cassette ref926, Box 85, Dvd ref926)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban, Fidel Mandela greeting, 1998; 467901 (Box 6, Cassette ref152, Box 77, Dvd ref152)
    This brief clips shows a greeting in Durban between Nelson Mandela and Fidel Castro. There are two versions, one with music and one without.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:02:32.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban, 1998; 477181 (Box 70, Cassette ref922, Box 85, Dvd ref922)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:22:07.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: "Pretoria (part 1) Soweto", 1998; 467905 (Box 7, Cassette ref148, Box 97, Dvd ref148)
    This video begins with on-the-street interviews in Soweto, South Africa with individuals gathered in anticipation of a visit by Fidel Castro. Interviewees explain why they are excited to see Fidel Castro, and several express their gratitude for Cuba's support of the fight against the apartheid government. The footage then changes to show Castro's arrival. The end of the video provides approximately 10 minutes of a rally honoring Castro. The speakers welcome Cuban and South African leaders and affirm the friendship between the two nations. Speakers also celebrate the memory of the Cuban revolution and Cuba's role in supporting democracy in South Africa.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:52.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 2), 1998 September 2; 467925 (Box 6, Cassette ref128, Box 97, Dvd ref128)
    This video largely features Nelson and Winnie Mandela greeting world leaders and delegates at the Non-Aligned Movement Summit in Durban, South Africa. Mandela can be seen greeting several prominent individuals including Yasser Arafat and Fidel Castro. At minute 18:04 the video features portions of Mandela's speech, which appears to have been recorded from a television screen or projector. The speech is not complete, but in it, Mandela speaks about the need for developed countries to commit to supporting those that are less developed. He specifically calls for the United Nations to support the people in Angola and Sudan.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:00.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 3), 1998 September 2; 467924 (Box 6, Cassette ref129, Box 97, Dvd ref129)
    This video begins with footage of Fidel Castro at the Non-Aligned Movement Summit in Durban, South Africa. The first 10 minutes feature Castro greeting other delegates and walking through crowds. At minute 10:32 the footage changes to portions of Castro's speech at the summit, which contains overlapping footage from video ref133. In the speech Castro calls for reforms with the United Nations, International Monetary Fund, and World Bank. He likewise criticizes wealthy nations, the United States in particular, for the proliferation of weapons, destruction of the environment, and the abuses of market capitalism.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:47.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 4) Interviews/Economic Crisis CNN Copy, 1998 September 2; 467920 (Box 6, Cassette ref133, Box 97, Dvd ref133)
    This video features a speech by Fidel Castro at the Non-Aligned Movement Summit in Durban, South Africa. Castro begins by thanking the leaders of the South African government, and calls for reforms with the United Nations to provide greater representation of countries in Asia, Africa, and Latin America. He specifically calls for an expansion of the Security Council and an end to permanent membership. He likewise criticizes the International Monetary Fund and World Bank, both of which he argues disproportionately benefit wealthy nations, and the United States in particular. In his speech Castro also criticizes wealthy nations development and sales of weapons, lack of respect for the environment, and displacement of people in the third world.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:42.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Durban (part 5) "Copy El Papa", 1998 September 2; 467919 (Box 6, Cassette ref134)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Fidel at Robben Island and Entering Soweto, 1998; 477186 (Box 69, Cassette ref927, Box 85, Dvd ref927)
    At Robben Island Estela Bravo interviews South Africans about Fidel Castro. There are scenes of a speech welcoming Castro followed by him talking with people and answering questions. The tape also contains footage in Soweto of Castro's arrival, and shows him placing a wreath on the monument to the 1976 uprising. The sound cuts in and out in several sections.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: Soweto (3), 1998; 467897 (Box 5, Cassette ref156, Box 77, Dvd ref156)
  - Footage of Fidel Castro in South Africa: "Transfers of Omar Chile Order Hope Robben Island", 1998; 467898 (Box 7, Cassette ref155)
  - Footage: Nelson Mandela and Fidel Castro, 1998 July 7; 479351 (Box 46, Cassette ref1013, Box 97, Dvd ref1013)
    This video features a series of clips of South African president Nelson Mandela visiting Cuba. The video begins with footage of Mandela arriving in Cuba where he is greeted by Fidel Castro. The bulk features Mandela and Castro at addressing crowds across Cuba, but does not contain any complete speeches. Much of the audio captured in these clips features informal discussions between the two leaders as they travel to different venues. Footage at the end of the video features Fidel Castro during a visit to South Africa, and ends with a segment of footage shot sometime earlier in which Mandela asks Castro to visit South Africa.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:48.
  - Footage: Various, Including Fidel Castro with Compay Segundo and Others, undated; 477052 (Box 68, Cassette ref850, Box 83, Dvd ref850)
    Some of the footage shows Fidel Castro at a reception for a group of doctors, which took place on Castro's birthday. There is black and white historical footage and, at the end, a there is footage of Castro with Hugo Chávez during a trip to Venezuela.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:39:21.
  - Footage: At a Reception, includes Fidel, Raúl Castro and Gabriel García Márquez, undated; 467872 (Box 5, Cassette ref181, Box 77, Dvd ref181)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:06:00.
  - Grenada Footage, 1998 August 1; 477171 (Box 70, Cassette ref912, Box 85, Dvd ref912)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:44.
  - Grenada Footage: Fidel "Casa les Ministro", 1998; 477169 (Box 70, Cassette ref910, Box 85, Dvd ref910)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:44.
  - "Grenada Speech", 1998; 467954 (Box 6, Cassette ref99)
  - "Grenada Airport - Fidel", 1998; 467926 (Box 6, Cassette ref127)
  - Info Packet, 2001; 590722 (Box 72, Folder 5)
  - Jamaica Footage: Lt. Governor Visit, circa 1998; 477170 (Box 70, Cassette ref911, Box 85, Dvd ref911)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:50.
  - Jamaica Footage: West Indies University Chancellor, circa 1998; 477168 (Box 70, Cassette ref909, Box 85, Dvd ref909)
  - Jamaica Footage: Fidel Speech in Mandela Park, 1998; 479330 (Box 46, Cassette ref1005, Box 97, Dvd ref1005)
    This video features a small portion of a speech by Fidel Castro at a ceremony celebrating the opening of Mandela Park in Kingston, Jamaica in 1998. Castro discusses European tourism, and argues that development of Jamaican tourism does not compete with tourist economies of other Caribbean nations, but rather represents a good sign for Caribbean tourism in general. Castro is then presented with the gift of a book by Jamaican spelling bee champion Jody-Anne Maxwell.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:06:35.
  - "Mandela Park - Patterson", circa 1998; 467927 (Box 6, Cassette ref126)
  - Footage: Castro Arriving in Montego Bay, circa 1998; 467950 (Box 6, Cassette ref103, Box 97, Dvd ref103)
    This video contains footage of Fidel Castro arriving to a celebration in Montego Bay, Jamaica. The bulk of the footage shows crowds of Jamaicans waiting along a street for Castro's motorcade to arrive. It also shows Castro arriving and greeting individuals in the crowd. At the end, a man can be heard off camera addressing welcoming Castro to the city.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:11:39.
  - Castro, Fidel: End of Speech in Mandela Park, Jamaica, circa 1998; 467947 (Box 6, Cassette ref106, Box 97, Dvd ref106)
    This video features the end of a speech by Fidel Castro in Mandela Park in Kingston, Jamaica. In this portion of the speech Castro discusses the need for Caribbean solidarity as a way to promote education and economic development in the region. He also calls for a greater dedication to the preservation of natural resources, protection of the environment, and support of neighbors after natural disasters such as hurricanes. At the end of the speech Castro is presented with a gift to thank him for visiting the city.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:15:19.
  - "Plaza - Sam Sharpe - Montego Bay", circa 1998; 467937 (Box 6, Cassette ref116, Box 97, Dvd ref116)
    This video features on-the-street interviews with crowds waiting for the arrival of Fidel Castro. In a series of brief interviews Estela Bravo asks individuals why they have come to see Castro speak and their opinions about him as a leader. Many express their admiration for Castro, specifically citing Cuba's role as a leader in education and healthcare in the Caribbean.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 0:24:54.
  - Crowd Footage: Castro Speech at Sam Sharpe Square in Montego Bay, Jamaica, circa 1998; 467909 (Box 6, Cassette ref144, Box 97, Dvd ref144)
    This video features footage of crowds in Montego Bay, Jamaica watching a speech by Fidel Castro. The footage focuses predominantly on individuals and their reactions to Castro's speech. Castro speaks in Spanish while his translator speaks in English, but the audio is only present in the background, while the video focuses predominantly on members of the crowd. The video starts and stops several times and as a result does not contain a complete recording of Castro's speech.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:59.
  - Grenada; Fidel Hotel Pegaso with Jamaican Governor, circa 1998; 467928 (Box 6, Cassette ref125)
  - News footage - Pierre Trudeau, etc., undated; 479371 (Box 62, Cassette ref1032)
  - Parts of Interview Translated Into English, 2001; 590732 (Box 72, Folder 20-21)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage - Miami, Little Havana, 1993 July 15, 1993 July 17; 477143 (Box 69, Cassette ref886, Box 85, Dvd ref886)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:20.
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; 479320 (Box 46, Cassette ref1002)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, includes Lucius Walker, 1993 July 17; 479323 (Box 62, Cassette ref1003)
    This tape is potentially damaged or unviewable.
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; 467981 (Box 3, Cassette ref72)
  - "Photos of Rangel, Mandela, Clinton, El Papa, and Hotel Teresa", 1996 August 10; 468034 (Box 2, Cassette ref19)
  - Photos of Alicia Alonso, Ramon Castro, Fidel Castro, Leonel Soto, Samora Machel, and Others, circa 1995-2000; 467979 (Box 2, Cassette ref74, Box 97, Dvd ref74)
    This video features still images of Fidel Castro and an interview with Cuban revolutionary Lionel Soto. The first 10 minutes features shots of still images of Castro with members of his family, including his oldest brother Ramón and his mother Lina Ruz González. Later photos feature Castro speaking to Cuban dancer Alicia Alonso after one of her performances. At minute 10:10 the video changes to an interview with Lionel Soto. Soto speaks about his memories of Castro and the student activist movement at the University of Havana. He describes student activism in period leading up to the Cuban revolution and Castro's role as a leader of that movement.
  - Presenting Fidel Documentary in Los Angeles, circa 2001; TW_TAM_616_ER_8 (Box Electronic Records, Folder TW_TAM_616_ER_8)
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro Speech (part 1), 2000 September 8; cuid376; 479367 (Box 47, Cassette ref1028, Box 96, Dvd ref1028)
    This video features footage of Fidel Castro's 2000 visit to the Riverside Church in the Harlem. The footage begins with a short speech by Bronx Congressman Jose Serrano welcoming Castro the New York City. The first 14-minutes feature individuals welcoming Castro and the crowd cheering for him and singing "Happy Birthday." At minute 14:30 Castro addresses the crowd and thanks them for their hospitality. He discusses his previous visits to New York City, and talks about several social issues like the blockade against Cuba, and maternal deaths and child malnutrition in the third world.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:18.
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro Speech (part 2), 2000 September 8; cuid377; 479368 (Box 47, Cassette ref1029, Box 96, Dvd ref1029)
    This video features the continuation of Fidel Castro's speech at Riverside Church in Harlem. In this portion of the speech Castro discusses the trade embargo and the effect it has had on Cuba's ability to obtain food and medicine. He also criticizes the globalized banking system and the problem of professionals from the third world moving to richer nations. He discusses Cuban solidarity with third world nations in Latin America and Africa, and praises the quality education and medical care in Cuba. This video stops and starts several times and does not contain a complete recording of the speech.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:34.
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro in New York (part 1), 2000 September 8; cuid378; 479391 (Box 62, Cassette ref1052, Box 96, Dvd ref1052)
    This video features footage from Fidel Castro's visit to the Riverside Church in Harlem in the year 2000. The bulk of the video features footage of the crowd waiting for Castro's arrival. At minute 1:55 Estela Bravo briefly interviews Bronx Congressman Jose Serrano about his opinions of Castro and the reason the crowd at the church is eager to hear him speak. At minute 10:16 the footage changes to an interview with an American diplomat who was part of the negotiations to return Elian González to Cuba. She talks about Castro as a negotiator and her perceptions of working with him on the González case. The footage also shows Fidel Castro arriving at the church and brief welcoming statements from various speakers.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:02.
  - "Riverside Church, Harlem (part 4), circa 1995-2000; 479395 (Box 62, Cassette ref1056)
  - Riverside Church, Harlem (part 5), circa 1995-2000; 467824 (Box 10, Cassette ref229, Box 97, Dvd ref229)
    This video features the final portion of Fidel Castro's speech at Riverside Church in Harlem. In this segment he thanks the American people who called for Elián González's return to Cuba, and those who protested legislation strengthening the trade embargo against Cuba. Castro then speaks about inequality and marginalization, which he acknowledges continues to exist in Cuba, and pledges his commitment to ending poor housing conditions and raising standards of living. Finally, he talks at length about what he viewed as overblown news coverage of his handshake with American President Bill Clinton, explaining that it lasted only a brief moment and the two men were simply trying to be polite.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:14.
  - Jesse Helms News Conference (part 1), 1995 February 9; 467816 (Box 10, Cassette ref237, Box 97, Dvd ref237)
    This video features a press conference hosted by United States senators and congressional representatives introducing the Cuban Liberty and Democratic Solidarity Act, later called the Helms-Burton Act. Senator Jesse Helms of South Carolina introduces the act and the goals of the legislation. Helms expresses his hope that the bill will lead to an end of Fidel Castro's leadership in Cuba and lead the country on a path away from communism. Co-author of the bill, Representative Dan Burton from Indiana speaks next and outlines the provisions of the bill, which places restrictions on U.S. trading partners who seek to trade with Cuba. Burton stresses the bi-partisan support for the bill and the stated goal of hastening the end of Fidel Castro's control in Cuba. Other speakers include representatives who contributed to the bill Lincoln Díaz-Balart, Bob Menendez, and Ileana Ros-Lehtinen.
  - Jesse Helms News Conference (part 2), 1995 February 9; 467828 (Box 10, Cassette ref225, Box 97, Dvd ref225)
    This video features a press conference with United States senators announcing the passage of the Cuban Liberty and Democratic Solidarity (Libertad) Act of 1996 also known as the Helms-Burton Act. Footage begins with a brief statement by Democratic Representative Robert Menendez of New Jersey, followed by a congressman from Florida, both of whom celebrate the bipartisan nature of the bill and express their hope that the bill will ultimately lead to the end of Fidel Castro's leadership in Cuba. Senator Jesse Helms ends the press conference describing the provisions of the bill, the restrictions it places on trade with Cuba, and expresses his hope that the bill will expedite the removal of Fidel Castro from power in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:53.
  - Script, undated; 590733 (Box 72, Folder 23)
  - Selection of Images "Yo Estuve Alli/ I Was There" (ICAIC), 2000 August 29; 477202 (Box 70, Cassette ref943, Box 85, Dvd ref943)
    According to Estela Bravo, this footage is a black and white documentary about the history of Cuba. This footage is not originally from one of Bravo's documentaries, but she used clips from it for her film Fidel.
  - State Council Footage: Scenes of Birán and other Fidel-related "Universidad Fidel de Casselle", undated; 467856 (Box 9, Cassette ref197)
  - State Council Footage: "Speeches Create Conscience", undated; 479362 (Box 62, Cassette ref1023)
  - State Council Footage: Includes footage in Chile, Colombia, and with Mohammed Ali, undated; 477187 (Box 71, Cassette ref928, Box 85, Dvd ref928)
    Much of the footage was filmed in Chile and Colombia. It contains an assortment of clips including: Castro meeting Latin American presidents; Gabriel García Márquez and his wife Mercedes; Castro speaking about inequality and justice; footage of Robert McNamara, Castro, and Jorge Risquet joking with each other around 00:27:00; a speech by Castro; and a celebration of Castro's birthday on plane. At 00:38:00 there is footage of a meeting in preparation for Pope's visit to Cuba. In another clip, Castro shows a set of Russian dolls and boxing puppets of himself and Bill Clinton, and around 00:56:00 there is a clip of a visit by Mohammed Ali and the Cuban boxer, Teofilo Stevenson. The sound drops out in intermittently throughout the video.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:04:49.
  - State Council Footage: Diane Sawyer, Dan Rather, and Others, 1998 August 7; 477188 (Box 71, Cassette ref929, Box 85, Dvd ref929)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:33:35.
  - State Council Footage: Fidel and Mandela, 1998 August 7; 477189 (Box 71, Cassette ref930, Box 85, Dvd ref930)
    The footage shows Fidel at the Rome Food and Agriculture Organization press conference in 1966; during visit to South Africa; at a reception line in Cuba; and in an interview with Diane Sawyer.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:31:33.
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 1) (airport arrival, speeches, greetings, Fidel kissing the Pope), 1998; 477191 (Box 70, Cassette ref932, Box 85, Dvd ref932)
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 2), 1998; 477192 (Box 70, Cassette ref933, Box 85, Dvd ref933)
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 3), 1998; 479345 (Box 46, Cassette ref1010)
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 4) (Dominican Cardinals), 1998; 479347 (Box 46, Cassette ref1011)
  - State Council Footage: ICAIC (The Cuban Institute of Cinematographic Art and Industry) Newsreels, undated; 477194 (Box 71, Cassette ref935, Box 85, Dvd ref935)
    There are a series of black and white clips on this tape. It contains older footage of Fidel Castro.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:10:01.
  - State Council Footage: ICAIC Newsreels, undated; 477195 (Box 71, Cassette ref936, Box 85, Dvd ref936)
    This tape contains a variety of black and white ICAIC film clips, which are in Spanish. They show Fidel Castro in many different settings such as state visits (including to Indira Gandhi), speeches, among the Cuban people, playing chess, hugging African leaders, and at a school. Some of the clips are older and some are duplicated on other footage.
  - State Council Footage: ICAIC Newsreels, circa 1980s; 477196 (Box 71, Cassette ref937, Box 85, Dvd ref937)
    This video includes five newsreels from ICAIC. They consist of a state visit by Mikhail Gorbachev; a visit by Jesse Jackson including a commemoration of Martin Luther King, Jr.; a brief piece of music and dancing; state visit by Socialist Spanish prime minister Felipe Marquez; and a commemoration of Cuban revolutionary fighter and intimate friend of Fidel Castro, Celia Sanchez.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:52:11.
  - State Council Footage: Archives ICRT, 1998 August 17; 477197 (Box 71, Cassette ref938, Box 85, Dvd ref938)